<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>hunt3ri.github.io - Mobile Games</title><link href="https://hunt3ri.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://hunt3ri.github.io/feeds/mobile-games.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://hunt3ri.github.io/</id><updated>2014-02-24T21:20:00+00:00</updated><entry><title>Casual Games – Designing for Success</title><link href="https://hunt3ri.github.io/casual-games-designing-for-success.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-02-24T21:20:00+00:00</published><updated>2014-02-24T21:20:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Iain Hunter</name></author><id>tag:hunt3ri.github.io,2014-02-24:/casual-games-designing-for-success.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Over the last 12 months our Studio has put out 3 games for Mobile Devices.  We’ve learned a number of hard, sometimes bruising, lessons along the way.  Today I want to talk about what makes Mobile/Casual games different, and some points you should keep in mind when designing games for mobile platforms.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Over the last 12 months our studio, &lt;a href="http://www.tsumanga.com/"&gt;Tsumanga Games&lt;/a&gt; has put out &lt;a href="http://www.tsumanga.com/our-games.html"&gt;3 games&lt;/a&gt; for Mobile Devices.  We’ve learned a number of hard, sometimes bruising, lessons along the way.  Today I want to talk about what makes Mobile/Casual games different, and some points you should keep in mind when designing games for mobile platforms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Casual" src="https://hunt3ri.github.io/images/hardcore-gamer.jpg#centre"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Fun, Fun, Fun&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you haven’t dipped your toe in the water of Mobile Gaming be prepared to drown in a sea of acronyms – CTR, CPA, CPI, DAU, MAU, IAP, LTV .  These things are important, and it behooves you to understand the space, but remember the cardinal rule:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If your game sucks – it won’t sell.&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everything comes back to making fun games that players enjoy, &lt;strong&gt;ALL&lt;/strong&gt; else is a distant second.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Casual Gamer != Hard Core Gamer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obvious right?  Casual Gamers play in short 2-10 minutes bursts, they like social experiences, many of them are women, yadda yadda.  However, often or more like – usually, the people who &lt;strong&gt;MAKE&lt;/strong&gt; casual games &lt;strong&gt;ARE&lt;/strong&gt; hardcore gamers, &lt;strong&gt;ARE&lt;/strong&gt; mostly male, and &lt;strong&gt;HATE&lt;/strong&gt; social experiences themselves 😉&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Casual" src="https://hunt3ri.github.io/images/casual.jpeg#centre"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m being a slightly facetious, the point is the Casual gamer often has a very different world view about games than the self-same people making those games.  They don’t have fond memories of the screee of a ZX Spectrum loading Chuckie Egg or pumping 50 pences into a Street Fighter II cabinet in a warm arcade with a sticky carpet.  Many of them weren’t even born when SFII was released!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So you need to get inside your customer’s head.  Casual Gamers don’t have huge ethical objections to the F2P business model, they don’t care Candy Crush is a Bejewelled rip, they expect games to be free (even if you’ve sunk 12 months of your life into your game), they will buy IAPs if well integrated, and they expect regular/very regular updates, which brings me onto…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Updates – Pile ’em High, Sell ’em Cheap&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Casual gamers &lt;strong&gt;YEARN&lt;/strong&gt; for updates, they cleave to them, they covet them.  Regular updates keep your players coming back for more, improve your conversion rate and so on.  So the tricky requirement from a game design pov is to balance what makes your game awesome, with making it quick and cheap to update.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you look at the undisputed champions of Casual Games – &lt;a href="https://supercell.com/en/"&gt;Supercell&lt;/a&gt;.  Both Hayday and Clash of Clans are great games but they can be very cheaply and easily updated.  When Supercell add a new building to Hayday the fans go batshit and all start grinding so they can have a Boathouse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the point is don’t create an epic space battle simulator that needs 6 months of effort to add a new level, because there’s every chance your game will die while you build it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Important from a production pov&lt;/strong&gt; – If you think it’s easy to optimise your Studio to release monthly updates of your games, you’ve clearly never built software or managed a typical dev cycle&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Feedback Loop – Listen to your players&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this world of Social Media and Cloud Services it’s stupidly easy to set up a twitter account, email account, Facebook Page to allow your players to send in their suggestions or more likely complaints (usually about the cost of everything). Do this, listen to your players and practice &lt;a href="https://blog.codinghorror.com/complaint-driven-development/"&gt;Complaint Driven Development&lt;/a&gt;.  Your players will love you, they will get the features they want and they generally know more about your game than you do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;and finally&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully these tips are useful, but remember the mobile space is a massively exciting field and a massively fast moving one.  To quote William Goldman –  Nobody knows anything.  So if someone tells you a “fact” (even me) about not doing something, but you believe it will work – try it – because for your audience it might just be the difference.  Except for $69.99 IAPs, don’t try those they are just plain a bad bad BAD idea, but for anything else…&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Mobile Games"></category></entry><entry><title>Introduction to Mobile Advertising</title><link href="https://hunt3ri.github.io/introduction-to-mobile-advertising.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-08-27T21:48:00+01:00</published><updated>2013-08-27T21:48:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Iain Hunter</name></author><id>tag:hunt3ri.github.io,2013-08-27:/introduction-to-mobile-advertising.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Many in the mobile industry see advertising as a dirty word, something to be avoided, a necessary evil – at best. This view is, perhaps, driven by the fact that the most successful games don’t have advertising – Minecraft, Clash of Clans, and lately Candy Crush Saga.  Of course it’s easy to promote life without ads when you’re making $2.4 million in revenues daily. I’d argue this view is mistaken&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Many in the mobile industry see advertising as a dirty word, something to be avoided, a necessary evil – at best. This view is, perhaps, driven by the fact that the most successful games don’t have advertising – Minecraft, Clash of Clans, and lately &lt;a href="https://www.gamasutra.com/view/news/194190/"&gt;Candy Crush Saga&lt;/a&gt;.  Of course it’s easy to promote life without ads when you’re making &lt;a href="https://www.pocketgamer.biz/news/50169/cash-of-clans-supercells-revenue-hits-24-million-a-day/"&gt;$2.4 million in revenues daily&lt;/a&gt;. I’d argue this view is mistaken&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Address Search" src="https://hunt3ri.github.io/images/dr-evil.jpg#centre"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Advertising when done well can add a significant percentage onto a developer’s bottom line.  The most famous example of integrating ads seamlessly with your product is, of course, Google – who now earn massive profits from returning ads along with search results.  Why can’t the rest of us integrate ads in a way that enhances or at least doesn’t alienate users and players?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many people still associate mobile advertising with cheap Banner Badgering.  However, the mobile ad industry is evolving at an extremely rapid pace, there are now all kinds of affiliate, interstitial, video, offer walls, to take into consideration.  Developers have reported that when done well ads are &lt;a href="https://www.gamesbrief.com/2012/03/how-to-make-3000-per-day-from-advertising-in-your-free-to-play-game/"&gt;adding $500-$3000 onto their daily revenues&lt;/a&gt; – a figure not to be sneezed at.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To that end I put together a presentation for the team at &lt;a href="http://www.tsumanga.com/"&gt;Tsumanga Studios&lt;/a&gt;, where I work.  To introduce some of the terminology and options that are available to games and app developers, I hope you find it useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src="//www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/key/2neDnkczY4iQNi" width="595" height="485" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" style="border:1px solid #CCC; border-width:1px; margin-bottom:5px; max-width: 100%;" allowfullscreen&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="margin-bottom:5px"&gt; &lt;strong&gt; &lt;a href="//www.slideshare.net/IainHunter1/introduction-to-mobile-advertising-25655683" title="Introduction to Mobile Advertising" target="_blank"&gt;Introduction to Mobile Advertising&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/strong&gt; from &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.slideshare.net/IainHunter1" target="_blank"&gt;Iain Hunter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Best Practice&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of the current crop of top games, take a look at &lt;a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.gameloft.android.ANMP.GloftDMHM&amp;amp;hl=en"&gt;Gameloft’s Minion Rush&lt;/a&gt; – the way they have integrated ads is very clever, rewarding users with tiny amounts of currency in exchange for watching an ad.  Similarly Disney’s Monsters University have integrated an offer wall in a way that doesn’t spoil the game at all for those uninterested in ads (note this is a paid for app).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Placing interstitial ads at appropriate points, ie at the end of a level (like Fruit Ninja) or rewarding the player for watching ads should not destroy the user experience, and may help your app break even faster.  At the very least, you should use ad networks to cross promote your other content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mobile app and game space is still pioneer country.  No one knows anything.  There are plenty people doing well with and without ads, but you need to make up your own mind and run your own experiments.  There are a number of competing business models out there, clearly if you can get your game or app right vast profits can be made.  That, however, is not an easy task.  Until you get it right, perhaps, ads can help?&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Mobile Games"></category></entry></feed>